<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on The User Centric Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on The User Centric Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2015 00:46:27 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>You need to empathise with your clients</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/not-empathetic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2015 00:46:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/not-empathetic/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;won-t-empathise-with-your-clients-you-won-t-solve-their-problems:027791d82044cc939ab9ebe9a3369d47&#34;&gt;Won’t empathise with your clients? You won’t solve their problems.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software applications are created for people to use. This is a pretty obvious statement for anyone who has ever turned on a computer or modern digital device, far less anyone involved in software creation. However, historically, it would be an alien concept to put users at the center of the software design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only recently do we see a trend towards trying to understand more about the user, their motivations, goals and required outcomes. This is a move in the right direction, we are beginning to empathise with our users, and this a good thing. But it&amp;rsquo;s just the beginning, we need to use that empathy as a driver for us (the development team &amp;lsquo;us&amp;rsquo;) to deliver a great product for our clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about UX in the enterprise. Changing how we think about our clients, who our clients are, why we should empathise with them and how we can use empathy as a driver to produce &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empathy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The psychological identification with or vicarious experiencing of the feelings, thoughts, or attitudes of another.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Dictionary.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I speak to some engineers about empathising with clients I hear comments that fall into the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why do we need to empathise when the requirements tell us all we need to know about the problem at hand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is this &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; going to improve anything?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sounds like an expensive waste of time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve gone native&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-empathise:027791d82044cc939ab9ebe9a3369d47&#34;&gt;Why empathise?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shared trust in the development process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See things from the client’s point of view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deeper understanding of the issue(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More creative problem solving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surface non-functional requirements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-can-we-develop-empathy-for-our-clients:027791d82044cc939ab9ebe9a3369d47&#34;&gt;How can we develop empathy for our clients?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn about your clients and their users&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out who the potential users are&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interview users with a structured questionnaire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visit the space in which the product will be used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the correct users to talk to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assess the scope of the project to see who could be affected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with the client to define your interviewees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t forget users on the periphery of the project scope&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interview as few people as is necessary to gain insight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interview your users and stakeholders&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask open ended questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take notes. Record the sessions if possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask users to demonstrate their current workflow if relevant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask users to draw their perfect future app, UI or process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try hard to shut up and listen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit the space where the product will be used&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch the user demo an existing workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look out for items used to support the workflow

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for notes on their desktop, crib sheets, calendars with annotation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch the user interact with others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immerse yourself in your notes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read, listen or watch your interviews&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assess any user sketches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write follow up questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start working with your client&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create personas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop story maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paper prototype UI workflows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host UX workshops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create user workflows with emotional states&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>